Over the years, there's different
standards, different agreements,
different terminology. It confuses the
AI, much like it confuses humans.
>> We're talking about how many times a
developer, how many X's in terms of 5x,
10x, 20x productivity gains are we
expecting to see?
>> What they found that influences actually
that X. If the task is more complex, it
could be that it's helping, but that
it's also requires you to tune and kind
of correct the agent right now. So, it
becomes a balance between how much
effort do I help, how much effort do I
actually know? The language on which the
LLMs have been trained, is that actually
a more popular language? Is it a niche
language? So, definitely also kind of
influences the code generation language.
>> The specs are bigger than code, because
if you change the spec, you can generate
the code from there. And that very much
aligns to our spec-driven development
that we often talk about as a way of
working.
>> Hello and welcome to another episode of
the AI Native Dev. My name is Simon
Maple, I'm your host for the day. And
today we're going to be talking
a lot about
a small little conference which happens
every now and then in San Francisco,
which is called the AI Engineering World
Fair. You may have heard of it. And
actually one of my colleagues, Patrick
Debois, who's been on the on the podcast
gosh, countless times now, uh, visited
the the conference a month ago or so,
when it when it whenever it was. And had
some had some really interesting TLDRs
and actually wrote a blog, seven lessons
from AI Engineering World Fair. So,
we're going to go through some of those
and
talk in depth in about one or two in
particular. But, but Patrick, welcome to
the podcast once again. You're a regular
here. You're almost You're almost
joining as often as I am. How are you?
>> I'm great. You can't really tell whether
it's me or any AI though, but we're all
good.
>> Well, I'll we'll assume it's an AI
unless unless you tell us otherwise.
How's that?
>> Yeah, let's do that.
>> Awesome. So, Patrick
So, Patrick, what what what do you do
these days?
>> Well, I'm having fun playing around with
the whole AI craze, especially now in
the space of coding and how it actually
is improving the SDLC. I feel like I'm
like discovering new ways of working
every day. And it's great like, you
know, on the community side and
everybody's sharing. It's It's It's a
lovely time to be alive.
>> Yeah. And you do a lot of contributions
to the AI Native Dev.
One of the, you know, major
contributions obviously was the
landscape. A
tool that allows you to
effectively keep up to date, keep track
of a bunch of AI Dev tools. That was one
of one of your kind of like big projects
into the AI Native Dev. One of the blogs
that you wrote as I mentioned was the
the seven lessons that you learned from
the AI Engineering World Fair. Tell us a
little bit about the AI Engineering
World Fair first of all as a conference.
It's in San Francisco, not one of my
most favorite places that I I tend to
go, but let's talk about that as well.
Uh
What's the conference like? What's the
vibe of it like? What's the Maybe I
shouldn't say vibe these days, but
what's the What's the the style of the
conference? Who are the typical people
who go? What's the type of sessions that
are there?
>> So, these days,
you know, when
everybody's talking about AI, I found it
really hard to find a conference that
actually is on point.
There's a lot of events that slap on
more AI, you know, I'm a traditional
developer conference and oh, we'll have
some talks on AI or we are already doing
in machine learning, so we'll do more AI
in there. So, there's a lot of events
happening out there, but I feel that
it's
bolted on and kind of like explaining a
little bit more of what it does. Mhm.
AI uh
engineer fair was actually one of the
first events that took it down center
like this is AI native. This is what
we're doing, right? It wasn't about all
the things of the past. It was all the
new things. And I think they've been
running this now like for 2 year 2 and
1/2 years.
And every time the event gets bigger. Uh
it's was organized by, you know,
initially it's still the same people,
but uh like from Swix. And he is also
the person who kind of like coined the
term a little bit the AI engineer and
kind of grew from there. So, it was like
a label AI engineer and they grew the
conference. Now, the cool thing about
this uh being um
so much on the spearhead of the new
technology is that all the new tools,
all the new people
all
even CTO CEU CEOs of those new tools are
still accessible because they all want
to be there. They all want to learn this
is where the head of the industry is
kind of going. That's why I love going
to these events because it is not just a
rehash of whatever we're doing. This is
kind of like where emerging patterns and
things learn. Obviously, there's always
kind of educational for people are not
that known with this. So, they have
workshops, but if you go into
their level of content, it is
forward-thinking. It is kind of like
things that like are on the edge
and I think they have also no shortage
of content because they stream most of
this just live for free. So, they
recognize everybody, you know, needs to
be there because it's all about the
community and the chat that you're
really learning. All the learns of the
videos are for free
um and it's just amazing how much energy
uh you have when you come in that room.
It's pretty big. I think they had like
roughly 3,000 people right now. So,
which is, you know, not bad for a
2-years-old conference.
But, yeah, they got the support from the
whole industry from big players all
around
and that's why I love going there. It's
not because I like San Francisco.
I'd gladly make an exception for this
event to go.
>> It's interesting actually cuz a lot of
events have in recent years, 5 10 years
or so, actually moved a little bit away
from San Francisco but these days
AI is obviously, you know, when you look
at a lot of the investment and a lot of
the startups they do tend to
focus very much at the at the core of
of San Francisco for for, you know, the
Silicon Valley space.
So, it kind of like makes it more
natural for AI engineers conference to
kind of like exist there which is I
guess why they why they keep it there
but it will be it will be interesting to
see
if they if they at any point do look to
to other places. I think earlier
this year they had
they had the AI engineers summit in New
York as well, right? Which is another
interesting
>> That one was more like uh
they called it invite-only. I think it
was still accessible in a way if you
really wanted to you could come but it
was not that you know the the ticket
sales are were kind of like open to to
everybody. And that's more of a
regrouping of that like smaller group
forward-thinking. So, the
for example, where in the past they had
like many tracks like you know, rag and
and so on they just had that whole
conference is going to be about agent.
So, they kind of like focused this
really hard.
So, one more invite-only, one open to
the very broad public.
And I
I keep hearing rumors there might be one
happening in Europe as well maybe in
fall. So, definitely they're thinking
about like doing this closer for us
closer to home. So,
>> Yeah. Yeah, absolutely. Um
Let's jump in. There are there are seven
learnings that you had. Should we should
we name them very very briefly? So, one
is about AI coding agents being truly
everywhere. The second one is about how
we need to change the way we we think
about using AI dev tools today. The
third is about how specs turning into
the new code. The fourth is about how
agents can be running in the cloud. The
fifth is about parallel execution and
how you can effectively
explore the results of AI
in in in parallel. The sixth is about
CICD and is that shifting left? And then
finally, the seventh is about the
productivity gains that people can get
from
from using AI and how many X's will it
deliver? Will it be a 2x, a 5x, a 10x?
We'll see. But, let's jump in with the
agents are everywhere and it does seem
In fact, there's a TLDR that I loved at
the top of your top of your blog, which
is I'll read it out. Cat ideas, pipe it
into specs, pipe it into parallel agents
which are which are running a
synchronously, pipe that into your
review and then pipe that into three dot
profit as normal
which I which I think is a nice a nice
TLDR. But, let's jump into that first
one, the the first learning.
AI coding agents are truly everywhere
and this is really about how everyone is
trying to effectively have an agent
mode, trying to showcase that that their
tool
is now supporting an agentic way of of
of working. Talk us through what you
what you saw there.
>> So, one one of the things to note on the
AI engineer is that
in the last couple of events
they were talking about agents and rag
and embeddings and fine-tuning and all
that stuff. So, the very broad AI
engineering.
For me, this event
was the first one who had
a large percentage of the talks focused
on coding. Where in the past, coding was
like, "Huh, yeah, it's there. Like, you
know, you use kind of a co-pilot and
that's done." But, because they're all
become so powerful, it it felt like the
tracks there was like a full track on
coding agents and and more of the bigger
player were announcing this. So, that
was truly everywhere in that sense that
yes, and the explanation is often that,
you know, you can look for a lot of use
cases to use more AI, but coding turns
out to be this amazing like valuable
piece to use AI for. So, that kind of
realization and it also shows in kind of
like what people are looking for in that
track. So, truly everywhere coding
agents is not just something on the side
that we do. It's just that in center
also at this event.
>> Yeah, and is it is it also showing that
as users we're trusting AI much much
more cuz we're leaning into that
autonomy? What what's what's the signal?
>> I think that's still
the the jury's out. So, all the vendors
are showcasing what they can do.
I think that like
I hadn't seen much of um
I am a company and I'm introducing all
these tools and that's the value I got
from. So, that's probably going to be
next year the more econic and how's
that? I think it did New York one that
it was one interesting talk about like
how booking.com kind of introduced us.
So, that was like the the biggest story
that I heard. Besides that, it's all
about the vendors kind of like defending
and saying how they improved this.
But, the stories are still a little bit
shy on that conference. So,
>> Yeah, yeah. Okay, cool. Let's go let's
jump into learning number two.
Interesting one.
Just in 6 months we're saying what what
what what this person saying here is if
you use AI tooling
like we did 6 months ago, we're making
mistake.
What's the what's the major difference?
Is it agentic again? What's the Is it is
it the fact that we need to run in a in
a agentic way? What's the what's the
what's the call here?
>> So,
um I would say that
in the past when you we have a new
technology, the cloud, mobile, and so
on. So, we see that initial spark, and
then we can say, "Oh, we just need like
a few more cycles to kind of like
polish, improve this. We can see where
this is going."
With the AI coding, it feels that every
6 months we'll have to reinvent the way
we actually use this. So, that's that's
was the one of the points that was made
uh by uh beyond uh from Sourcegraph who
said like,
"You have a practice like, 'Oh, I can do
completion.' All right. Oh, no. All of a
sudden I have an agent. So, I'm I'm
doing prompts now. So, I'm kind of that.
And then after the prompts, somebody
said like, 'Okay, we're doing agents,
but now it becomes about specs.' So, we
see that kind of reframing
is important. And so, one of the biggest
mistake is actually that you keep using
the completion and say, "I got it."
Right? So, you have to kind of keep
embracing
like new possibilities by the new kind
of technology that's being embedded in
the tools. And we're still figuring out
like what the ideal kind of workflow
looks like, but every time every 6
months we're unlocking with a certain
new set of tools
uh kind of a new way of working, which
is great uh in that perspective.
There were some like interesting like
smaller tidbits on for example, OpenHand
saying
um you know, in the past we would say,
"Agent, run off. Come back to us." And
and and we see the pull requests of an
agent's happening. And agent A does
this. Agent B did that.
But they found that it wasn't about um
they needed to actually to have a human
that was responsible for the actions.
So, they started changing the way that
the PRs were actually on behalf of a
user because
they found out that like people respond
better to user than to an agent telling
us what to do, right? Right. Well, it
could be the other way around as well,
but they they kind of like turned this
into that it was always like this agent
did did that on behalf of that user. So,
that was a smaller thing, obviously,
to the dirt. And then there like the
other thing was, "Oh, we we just got
used to using it more in our IDEs and
the things." And all of a sudden we
switching to more terminal based CLI
tools. And
maybe that's the part where like more
autonomous asynchronous because it's
happening somewhere it runs, we don't
have to see it that much anymore, and it
comes back to us when it's done.
One of the newer typical features from
those AI things is that they have a
notification. We all know notifications,
we hate them, right? Our social media,
our internal chat systems, and now the
agents will send us like, "Hey, we're
done. Like, you need to do something."
Because that asynchronous thing is also
kind of changing how we interact with
them.
>> And it's really interesting actually
because yeah,
you mentioned, you know, obviously
things like Claude Code, you've got
Codex, Gemini model now. That's that
that's has a kind of like Is it TUI or
Chewy? Which would you go for?
>> Um
I terminal UI, I would say.
Chewy, that could be in Belgium like a
a travel agency as well. So,
>> Oh, yeah, yeah. We yeah, we Okay, yeah,
let's not use that then. So, TUI.
So, so your T UI.
So, yeah, you get things like Claude
Code, obviously, that
it really does It's one of the It's one
of the first ones that really does
change the well, first
first tools that that has gone gone kind
of like mainstream to really change the
way in which developers code
because it's entirely terminal based.
A lot of the way that I see people use
that though, they don't just stay in
Claude Code and continue to to to, you
know,
prompt and only stay in that terminal. A
lot of people that I know of that use
Claude Code, make the changes, then they
you know, see the changes not in the
terminal per se, but in
in their
typical IDE. And so, they're bouncing
between the two. So, while we look at
things like Cloud Code being headless,
it's not the headless experience that
we're always that that you know, we
stick to. It's the tool that is headless
and we're actually still
sitting in our IDE of choice to to
really
if we want to look at the code more and
more to to be able to traverse the code,
to understand what the code's doing, to
be able to do those reviews. And then
you effectively use whatever it is,
whether it's Git or something like that
to effectively do your rollbacks and and
and uh maintain state um of your of your
versioning. Is that Would you say that's
fair across
>> Remember that we talked about you using
the old paradigms from 6 months ago. And
the the 6 months ago, we were chatting.
So, having a chat with an agent was a
very synchronous thing. So, you could
definitely use a terminal to do the same
thing. You just chat and you kind of
have this happening.
Now, people have been saying it's the
end of the IDE.
Um
you could say maybe it's the end of the
code editor, but you'll still have to do
the review. So, somehow you need UI or
some way of like explaining things. As
you mentioned, like when it's done, you
kind of like have to visualize and see
whether it's it's okay.
So, it's it's it's not completely
headless, but it could go off if you
would say if you really embraced like
the asynchronous coding way, you would
give it a larger chunk of tasks
and it runs for a couple of hours and
then it comes back to you. So,
that's the same thing. Like but that
means you'll have to specify more up
front than just that simple task or that
one thing. Or otherwise, it's more
guessing and you don't have to stay in
that loop. So, that's why it is you can
use a technology
in the more synchronous way, but if you
embrace asynchronous way, you start
doing more of those kind of
specifications and bigger tasks that you
need to do.
>> And talk about specifications as your
learning number three, how specs are the
new code. Um and I think this is kind of
like we're seeing this being mentioned
more and more and I think specifically
at this event, it was Shawn Grove who
um works at OpenAI and he was talking
about a number of things called model
specs and things like that. Um give us a
kind of brief overview. We shared this
video of course at Tesla behind the
scenes as well cuz it was very on on on
the mark for us. Um tell us a little bit
about how OpenAI are thinking about
model specs and specification.
>> So they talked about a spec being
important to guide a model for certain
generation. And internally they have a
concept called a model spec. And in that
model spec they say things like you
should always be friendly to what you're
generating. It should be always on
point. If you don't know the things, you
should do that. So
they kind of
the example he gave was more about like
training a model and making the model
actually respond to those things.
But the same you can actually then apply
to not training the model, but asking
the model what to do. So if you give it
specs to do a certain task or to code
it, you kind of like give it that longer
or that bigger chunk and it does it. If
you want to change something, it's not
about like the kind of disposable
prompts that you never record. You just
change the spec and you generate from
that again. So that kind of reasoning
for model training with specs and then
code training or code generation with
specs kind of like started to coincide
in that kind of presentation.
And what was really nice is that he said
um
it actually they use it for alignments
of the models and the AI.
But what he also said was writing
specification actually aligns the humans
because you have to agree what the task
is at hand. So, there's a benefit from
kind of both sides and human and uh
I explained it sometimes as what you're
describing for a model is almost like
your code of conduct of your model. Like
this is how I think you should behave
and you kind of bake that into the
model. But very similar for your code,
this is how I want you to write my code.
This is my directory structure, this is
my language, these are my coding
conventions, this is my process that I'm
doing. So, you can all put all those
things in in in the specs. And so, hence
he just, you know, like concluded like
the specs are bigger than code because
if you change the spec, you can generate
the code from there. And that very much
align to your old expect driven
development that we often talk about uh
as a way of working. So, it was a
surprise coming from that angle from
OpenAI model training and then all of a
sudden like, you know, kind of crossing
the chasm to code generation and saying
actually it's it's there uh valid as
well. So,
>> Yeah. And I think you mentioned in the
blog as well how tests play such an
important role in effectively being able
to validate
uh specifications. So, obviously a
specification is we're going to need to
have some implementation created from
that. And it's the tests that are
written that uh that need to need to
validate that. I guess some would say,
"Okay, the tests are part of that
specification."
Um
and some would say, "Actually, the tests
are actually more important then as a
result than than the code." Uh because
they they they're proof of your intent.
Um how much how much was that kind of
like mentioned cuz I feel like that's a
a very crucial part.
>> I think he said uh what isn't uh in
like
if it isn't specified in the
specification that behavior
then
it's actually it shouldn't be important.
So if you really need it to be written
down it needs to be in the specification
and it be there. But we all learn from
executable documentation remember that
word
a couple of years ago and it's the very
same thing. So if you were write like
the cases that actually it should work
with that are the tests and they're an
integral part of kind of examples
obviously in AI you would do this the
multi
kind of examples in your prompt but this
is very similar to your tests being
described.
I personally believe that this helps
actually with the generation because you
know the actual
LLM will look at the the the tests or
the examples and try to figure out
whether that works or not. Now
the jury's still out whether we can
trust this like completely but that's a
different story. But the fact that we
can now also it generates the test that
still relieves the human to actually
verify whether the tests were generated
whether they were correct and actually
the specification will help again with
that alignment as well because now we
can see the examples in the specs so the
human can also kind of verify whether
the behavior was correct. in both ways.
>> It's interesting actually because I I I
met up with Baruch who I
we had on the podcast
a couple of weeks ago. And one of the
things that he was talking about was
around using an existing framework like
like you know Gerkin and Cucumber so
Gerkin specs and Cucumber the tool that
allows you to create that BDD style
approach.
His approach to something like this is
to be able to create
a set of test descriptions effectively
in the
Gerkin format that could then be
validated as
you know natural language and so you can
kind of like look at it and say yeah I
agree I agree I agree and and you're
effectively effectively part of your
specification then right cuz it's it it
shows that intent and then
using something like Cucumber to then
turn that into tests there's no LLM it's
it's there's no non-determinism you know
so long as you get it right in your
given that given this then that
so long as that's right then you will
get those tests that actually that
actually perform that and you have that
greater level of
of of
confidence that those tests are going to
be correct
>> developer actually writes that code
right like you know
fulfills that test so it is the business
person kind of describe the business
functionality thanks to a behavioral
test and then that gets implemented now
you can use that same kind of language
to specify things in your examples for
example
no pun intended but the
then the LLM just generates from that
the actual code and something that
adheres to
the BDD test that you provided still
it can get it wrong so we're not there
that it's 100% but it actually makes
that mapping even more seamless like I
don't have to write that code I can like
bootstrap the code and eventually have
almost like perfect code to run this and
see them execute from the code I have
and so in that loop that an agent goes
through it wasn't that what we're
looking for for a completion or the
initial chat but with an agent you can
go into a loop and say oh it didn't work
let me look at the or error
kind of let me run that test again so
that kind of loop
is now more
has more context to what it actually
should be achieving there
>> cool
almost halfway now
four number four is agents to the cloud.
So, this is about how people aren't
using agents in their kind of like local
local machines anymore. This is more
about how they can be pushed to the
cloud and then executed
somewhere further away.
Talk us through I guess
Is this something that you're seeing
fairly
fairly commonly
you know, rolled out across different
tooling vendors and different providers?
>> So, the the struggle you have with more
of these async longer running threads is
when you close your laptop it goes to
sleep.
You have like some annoyances there. So,
that was one thing like you know, I have
a longer running and it will not keep
running. The second one is
if I run these agents and they they do a
lot of CPU work, it's hogging my
machine. So, that's also kind of
annoying. So, you know, how do you solve
that problem as well. And then the third
one which you start more and more
appearing is if you do it parallel, then
it becomes even more constrained to do
this.
Now, where do you start like seeing this
in a tool?
Maybe the first one you could say was
the amp code was doing code indexing
from your embeddings into the cloud. If
you have large code bases, your machine
doesn't have a GPU, it takes a lot of
time to do all that local indexing. So,
they resorted to moving that to the
cloud. Now, that's a minor thing, but
it's definitely helpful for bigger code
bases there as well.
Now,
what then you start seeing tools like
cursor you know, trying background
agents. And so, they they have like a
hosted version of that like execution
thing.
And now all all the others are kind of
like following suit that like you can
have the option either run the agent
locally or run it on a remote machine.
Now, there's a bit of a challenge here
is how do we actually replicate the
environment
>> Mhm.
>> of your dev environment somewhere in the
cloud. So,
that the first attempt was let me like
almost like create a virtual
like shadow environment from your coding
environment and we'll code on that. So,
that was one of the first tries and
becomes immensely complex because
like what's all the things that have
been set up and you just can't say clone
dev environment or so specific so kind
of annoying. So, that's where people
move more into hey, but we have this
technology called containers and so we
use that in our CI/CD. So, let's kind of
run these agents in those kind of more
sandbox environments and then obviously
that became like the logical thing to do
either in a local sandbox in your
container or somewhere in the cloud.
Now, that means
they're mostly shifting towards
the following pattern.
I have an existing code commit and I
want to do an update on that commit and
then I ask the agent to do a certain
task on that commit, right?
So, what they do behind the scenes is
they say here's the commit. Oh, let me
kind of do a get pull from the repo
check out that commit, run my agents in
the cloud, and then I kind of like
create a feature branch and present that
back to you. So, that's kind of the flow
that all these tools have been following
to make it all more lot easier to have
like a more reliable workflow than
trying to clone your desktop which is
kind of like insane
>> Mhm.
>> and would not work.
So, it's definitely there more and more
in the tools. Now, running agents is not
also without any issues.
Like you have to do the permissions. And
if you're still doing the babysit
version of yes, no, agree that's great,
but that's for a a running thread that's
going to be annoying, right? So, if you
can kind of control the network, which
tools it has access, you can control
that way better in a sandbox environment
than trying to run on your laptop as
well to do that. So, those are like two
reasons why people are moving towards
the cloud and it like the major coding
tools are doing this. Now, whether your
whole IDE will move to the cloud or we
still have an IDE, that's a different
conversation, but you start seeing uh I
think um
Cursor just released like a mobile uh
view
on their editor, so you can kind of code
from mobile. So, you see kind of
something is shifting again on how we
deal with this and and how it reports
back to you when it's done um in there
as well.
>> I didn't see the mobile. Was that Was
the mobile Cursor uh view was that um
Was that also at the AI Engineer Summit
or is that more recent?
>> No, no, it's uh it's something that
released like last week or something
like that.
>> Oh, wow. I didn't see. I missed that.
Wow, it it it's such a fast-moving
space, right? It's very hard to It's
very hard to catch it all. Um very, very
interesting. And And one of the things
that that kind of like opens up as you
kind of mentioned there was was
parallel. Obviously, if you're trying to
run multiple agents in parallel, it's
going to be a real consumption hog for
your for you know, your local machine.
And that kind of like leans us into
your fifth learning, which is around
parallel execution. And there are I
guess a few reasons you might want to do
something like this. And And And in your
in your blog, you mentioned a few things
that were kind of mentioned. One is a
really around breaking a task up uh into
into subtasks and having multiple
different agents work on those subtasks.
And I think I guess
somewhat you could actually it's nicer
to almost like have different uh models,
I guess, potentially working on those
depending on what the right model is for
that um for for that task. Um others,
you might have um
uh just a variety. So, let's let's have
three perhaps different models or maybe
the same model running something three
uh times in parallel and then trying to
work out, okay, which is the which is
the best one that I want to go with. And
it really does open up this
this new world whereby because we are
with the genetic coding waiting longer,
we can afford to kind of like say, yeah,
run a few. Let's Let's try and now get
the best answer.
And I don't mind if it takes an amount
of time. Just come to me when you're
done and we'll we'll we'll sync up
what's um
you know, what what what's been created.
It really opens a new world for us,
right?
>> Yeah, yeah.
So, you're right. Like two pieces, one
is faster delivery or split this up a
parallel. We actually do this
intuitively, you know, without agents.
Like let's have five developers. Let's
split up the features, kind of go from
there and then, you know, they can work
and merge in and be more like
independent of each others.
Like now the the planning is actually
done by the coding tools and they kind
of try to split this up. Now, it is
challenging which actually you know,
thing overlaps with another tool because
they have the same problems as humans
have is in the end you need to do the
merging of all those parallel things.
You could use things like stacking or
like a few of those changes together. Um
but yeah, that's that's the first reason
why people use this and and they have
some challenges. Uh the other is
variations and it could be
uh things like um I want to like explore
three different ways of solving this
problem, right? So, use this framework,
use that framework, use that framework.
Or
come back with three hypothesis why the
performance is bad. Like an explore
three of them. So, it could be also be
for
performance or support reasons there as
well.
>> So, so I like that whereby you can
almost like say to the LM that created
this, okay, why is yours better than
these others? So, almost like
almost like argue between each other as
to which is the best. Or maybe there's
some there's some
uh you know spot in the middle where
actually it's maybe less performant but
actually there are other things that
that go for it more reliable or whatever
it is. Um whereby actually they can come
to a decision based on their own
discussion their own arguments as to as
to why each are best.
It's like the the the it's bizarre how
great this could actually turn in.
>> Yeah. But that's that's a challenge,
right? So imagine
uh as a human we have five people doing
coding in the different tracks.
There's one kind of orchestrator or
something or manager who's to say well,
this is the best.
>> Mhm.
>> Um Now
in most of the tools you will find that
they're all about good about creating
all these variations.
But they actually that brings the burden
on us, you know, kind of like managing
which one is the best. Now we could use
maybe some help from an LLM who says
like I think based on the input that the
other agents gave me, I think this one
is the best. So
or it could help us also show different
diffs like
>> Mhm.
>> this kind of application that like or
gave measurements. Now
I feel that
this is the field where kind of we're
moving into. Like now we have parallel
execution. Now we need a way better way
of doing that review or parallel review.
Now some of the tools are starting to
build the new UI in a way that is not
showing one version of the application
but it allows you to compare three
versions of the application
kind of more in parallel or three kind
of like rendered things.
And and we'll see more of that.
You know, I was once talking with one of
our colleagues Tom and and we came up
with an idea like
we often asked to do vibe coding, you
know, to kind of build an app. But what
if the agents actually can vibe code an
application to do the review?
>> Mhm.
>> Because then it becomes easier to kind
of like say which one is the best. the
They come up with the best interface to
actually check whether like what's the
best that we should select. So there's a
lot of like exploration to be done
there. But the burden of reviewing still
stays on us. So anything we can do to
improve that, reduce cognitive load,
help us understand. That's probably the
next phase in in whole this journey
of going there. So
>> Yeah, and and the developer usage you
kind of mentioned in the post as well
that
Solomon Hykes, the CEO of Dagger, one of
the things that that they showed was how
you can effectively hook up an MCP
server or you can invoke
through your IDE an MCP server whereby
if you say I want some different
variations for this, it'll go away and
do that from an MCP server and actually
when you pull the changes back that it's
already in a branch. Each each
variation's in a branch each and each
you can kind of like click through, have
a look at them, and then merge
merge the branch that you want to
accept. So from a from a user point of
view it's actually very very aligned
with potentially the way that developers
want to consume these changes. It's not
some completely different UI or anything
like that. It's nicely within the their
IDE which is wonderful.
>> Yeah, and I think that's that's also a
journey that we've seen. So
last year I saw quite some tweets about
let's open up five different IDE windows
and have them all code on the same code
base. Disaster, chaos, you know,
obviously from experiment.
Then the next kind of phase was well,
what if we clone the directory to kind
of like and have them work on separate
and kind of merge that back in. So that
was the whole idea of get up work trees
and kind of get work trees to kind of
like have different
like agents working on each other that
the environments weren't isolated enough
because you need to control more and
then we put in a container and then
ultimately be we put that into the cloud
there as well. So that that
parallelization has been going on for a
while and what you see now is that when
you run it in the cloud, how do you
actually merge this back in?
Cursor has this
behind the scenes is not very well
described but they call it like a the
remote
kind of cursor protocol which is
emerging from a remote server back to
your local branch and then kind of
dagger has a similar system where it
actually exist in a container but you're
almost as simple as a get merge get like
whatever was in the container back to
your local code thing thing there as
well. So
again another learnings and how it's
progressing on like all bits and pieces
they come from intent
kind of break it down to task which we
did like parallel and then kind of do it
this parallel execution and now we're up
to the reviewing as kind of the issue
whether we like it or not. So that's the
next frontier there. So
>> Yeah. Yeah, very interesting. Looking
forward to seeing where that goes.
Learning number six, let's move on to
learning number six. Is CICD shifting
left? This one baffled me. Tell me how
CICD can can can shift left Patrick.
>> So um
with all those agents kind of putting
more
and having specifications having
examples
they do a lot more testing than maybe we
would continuously do.
So that means that like whenever you're
still
on your local branch, you can spin up
the same CICD and have the agents kind
of almost kind of run that. So in that
perspective it is shifting even more
left like not all the testing has to be
done on the CICD system but we can do
like, you know, code analysis or other
stuff. Now, this was possible in the
past as well, but now that we've moved
into the parallel execution and the
parallel thing, we we we we get that to
a bigger extent where in the past it was
always like, "Yeah, in the CI/CD it has
the real environment, it has the real
setup." But what if you can just like
take that simple system and have the
agents have their own CI environment and
do the same thing? So, we get way master
faster feedback as a developer and don't
have to wait until the whole merge is
complete until it kicks off. So, that's
was the whole idea of CI/CD uh is
shifting left with kind of faster
feedback to the developer even before
anywhere like merging this into one of
the main systems or kind of the staging
system. So, yeah.
>> Yeah, interesting. And and um
you kind of also mentioned that um
Josh Albrecht
uh in Blue CTO uh just talking a little
bit about how uh specs with strict
guidelines helps catch these issues
earlier in the in in the value stream.
And I think this is all about um the
kind of intent, making it easier, being
able to really clearly describe intent
makes it easier to be able to validate
whether your implementations adhere to
that intent or don't adhere to that
intent. Is that Is that Is that fair?
And is it from a from a spec point of
view, is it easier for us to kind of
like generate tests and and and uh
really build out the tests that are
important because we're very clearly
defining intent?
>> Yeah. I think um
when we
code traditionally, we take
specifications either from, you know,
your product manager what it's supposed
to do, and we break this down into
actual code.
Now,
imagine you would then run a security
scanner or something on that, and you
just run this on the code. The code is
just an implementation as such. But
imagine would actually know what the
intent or the intended behavior was. It
could do a way better job at
understanding what it needs to check. So
it's almost like that we throw away that
information and like in a game of
telephone and then like assume the next
kind of agent just like our tool knows
it. So if they can all refer to that
same spec, they have a better chance at
collecting actually understanding what
goes on. So
it's it's funny because it's it's
actually almost like a when you're
making a movie, you you
you kind of remove all the cuts, you
remove all kind of the the takes and
then you only have the last thing and
then you don't know anymore how actually
the movie was made because
but when you need to do it again, you're
like, what what lightning did I use or
like what what like okay. So kind of
very similar of throwing away metadata
at the end of the pipeline.
>> And and going back to I guess your third
learning there when you talk about specs
of the new code, one of the things that
Shawn was mentioning is how
specifications align humans and what
we're really talking about here is it's
not just aligning humans, it's aligning
aligning agents through the through the
through the workflow to make sure they
all have that access to that that core
intent data and the core the core data
that we're we're using throughout the
creation process.
Cool. Last one Patrick.
How many X's will AI deliver? And we're
not talking about the the the funky I'm
still going to call it new the funky new
name brand for Twitter. We're talking
about how many times
a developer or how many you know, X's in
terms of 5x, 10x, 20x
productivity gains are we expecting to
see? Are
we are we really looking at the kind of
like 5x, 10x, 20x style claims uh,
that people are making or or is this
overblown?
>> So, at the event, uh, there was a
researcher, um,
kind of explaining,
uh,
you know, what they found that
influences actually that X. Uh, and it
could be if you're doing a simpler task,
right? Of course, the AI is better at
this and so that gives you a performance
boost. So, if you're doing that
repetitively, you get like an X that is
bigger.
If the task is more complex, right? Uh,
it could be that it's helping, but that
it's also an
it requires you to tune and kind of
correct the agent right now way more.
So, it becomes a balance between how
much effort do I help, how much effort
do I actually know. So, that kind of
influences that.
The other point that he made is, uh, if
you have a code base that has been long
running,
um,
there over the years there's different
standards, different agreements,
different terminology. It confuses the
AI, much like it confuses humans, I
guess. But that means the effectiveness
goes down. If I ask a question, well, it
says like, "Well, where are my coding
standards?" Well, you had like seven
different over like five years.
Uh, so that inconsistency actually also
influences that. Uh, obviously the
bigger size, but that seems to be
overcome by having bigger machines to
index the code base.
Uh, and kind of find the relevant pieces
that need to be changed. So, that is a
factor, but it's it's maybe a less uh,
thing. And then the last one he
mentioned was the language on which the
the LLMs are have been trained. Uh, is
that actually, you know, a more popular
language? Is it a niche language? So,
definitely also in in in kind of
influences, uh, the code generation
language. Now, all of that is always a
snapshot in time and all these points
they valid, but then we saw that it was
not just about the LLM, just doing one
code generation. It was going into a
loop, and then the loop got
documentation, got specs. So, there is a
different like definitely a rise on
this, but it it's not like a excess or
something. Um but it it is
there is a certain influence that,
depending on your use case, you might
not be getting what you others are
saying about their code base. If it's
like a small, new, modern language, kind
of like fresh, it's completely different
than a more legacy enterprise or kind of
like tool base that that you're working
on. So, that was kind of his finding
uh where he says, "Most of those um are
you more efficient with AI?" is very
anecdotal because they they didn't kind
of specify these aspects. And then it
becomes like, "What are you actually
comparing?"
Yeah, that we're working on, so.
>> Yeah.
Well, I think one of the big takeaways
from this whole thing is really that,
and I think you mentioned this in your
closing thoughts as well.
Uh and let me read from it. What is
considered good practice now can change
really fast and it's hard to keep up.
And I think that's one of the That's one
of the core kind of things in particular
in one of your one of your learnings,
which is around
uh you know, using even 6 months ago
an AI tool in the same way as today,
you'd you'd actually be, you know,
pretty
you know, doing it pretty poorly or not
not really using the most effective
means of of developing. So, it's like
you're going to change again in another
6 months, and it's really really
important to to stay on track and to and
to keep learning because uh
you know, today we have TUIs and agents
and cloud agents and things like that.
Who knows where we're going to be in 6
months. Uh any any predictions if I put
you on the spot there, Patrick?
>> Um
What predictions is the reviewing is
going to get a bump, and then after that
is going to be knowledge management.
Because if if we got more automated, we
have to kind of keep track of all the
learnings that the agents are doing and
kind of spend more more time on that. I
I understand it's very frustrating to
have to keep checking what the tool do,
how it's actually improving,
and a lot of people are dismissing, "Oh,
I looked at tool X and it didn't work
for me."
But then maybe next day they kind of
bumped and they improved the whole
version
or they did differently. And that's kind
of the annoying is that like whatever
uh and I I I often refer to this as the
innovation tax, right? So, you you just
have to pay that tax of having to try a
new tool, but it's definitely different
from previous waves of technology where
you say, "Oh, it's maturing." And now
it's like constantly changing
how we work, which doesn't really help
to that kind of perspective, I guess.
>> Yeah. And I think as us as developers
need to kind of
always be open to that constant learning
and never never thinking if I'm you
know, I'm using this today,
um I'm going to stay on this for the
next couple of years. It's just not
possible right now. You have to
absolutely keep looking and have to keep
updating and and and and taking on the
new the new features, the new ways of of
of doing things.
Uh Patrick, once again, it's been
absolutely amazing to chat with you.
Really really appreciate all your all
your kind learnings, sharing your kind
learnings not just on the blog, which
we'll share in the show notes,
but as well on our podcast. So, really
really appreciate you joining and thanks
thanks again for for supporting the AI
Native Dev.
>> Yeah, my pleasure. And also kind of as a
listener or viewer, if you have like a
cool story you want to share or
something that you know, you learned, do
feel free to reach out or put in the
comments or like we're always kind of
like
willing to see what others are doing.
So, that's cool.
>> Absolutely. Absolutely. Thank you very
much. And thanks everyone for for tuning
in. Really, as Patrick mentioned,
interested to hear if uh if you went to
the AI engineering uh world uh fair.
What did you think? What were your
takeaways? And uh thanks for tuning in
as well. So, till next time. Bye for
now.